Okay, so today we will discuss the Bronze Age collapse.
好的，今天我们要讨论古代黄土壳的崩溃
I want to paint you a picture
我想给你们画一幅画
of the world in about 1200 BCE.
大约1200年后回到古代黄土壳的画面
So, in this world,
好的，先在这片大地里
the center of this world
好的，先在这片大地里，先后??
is what we call Mycenaean Greece.
好的，先后????
Okay, across from the Mycenaean Greece,
好的，跨越古希腓里…
across the Aegean Sea, okay, this is the Aegean,
好的...??…
is what we call Anatolia.
??…
Today we refer to Anatolia as Turkey, okay?
今天我们把安塔尔尼亚称作土耳古里亚
And in Anatolia,
the Hittite Empire
...
rules Anatolia.
规则安塔尔尼亚。
Further south is a place called Cyprus.
进一步南方有一个叫做柯普利亚的地方。
Canine, okay? Canine is important
Canine...??…
when we do the Bible
...
because that is the birthplace of the Israelites.
??
Okay, so Canine today is what we refer to as Lebanon,
好的，...
Syria,
翻译：
and Israel today.
...
Canine is a province of the Egyptian Empire, okay?
Canine...??…
So this is Egypt, okay?
??
Over here,
在此处，
is a place called Mesopotamia.
And we today call Mesopotamia Iraq.
在此处，伊斯兰语为伊拉克。
Okay? Over here is today what we call Iran.
在此处，伊斯兰语为伊拉克
Back then it was basically Persia.
回到那时，基本是波斯。
Over here is Afghanistan.
在此处是阿富尼亚。
And then next to Afghanistan is India.
接着在阿富尼亚旁边是印度。
And of course, remember these are the steps.
Okay? So for Mesopotamia and Greece, you also had the Mediterranean.
好的？所以在美索波提亚和希腊里，你们也有地中海。
And over here are the islands of Cyprus and Crete.
在此处是塞浦里亚和克里特岛。”]}We need to translate cues [31] and [32] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural Chinese. Let's translate: cue 31:
And then over here is a place called Iberia.
在此处是伊比利亚。
And over here is Britain.
在此处是英国。
Okay? So
...
this is a map
???
of the world in 1200 BC.
And what's really important for you to recognize about this world is it's interconnected.
在此处是伊比利亚。
Meaning that they are trading and communicating with each other.
在此地是英国。”
Okay? This is what we call the Bronze Age.
好的？这就是我们所说的青铜时代。
The Bronze Age.
青铜时代。
And why is it called the Bronze Age?
为什么叫青铜时代？
Because they're trading basically bronze during this period.
因为在此期间他们基本上在交易青铜。
Back then, bronze is like oil today.
回到那时，青铜就像今天的石油。
Okay? It is the basis for the economy.
好的？它是经济的基础。
The very structure of their economy.
铜的结构就是其经济结构。
Bronze is an alloy made of copper
铜合金
and tin.
和锡。
Copper and tin you have to mine.
铜与锡你需要开采。
Okay? And only a few places will have these resources.
OK? 只要几处…
So tin is found in Britain,
在英国、伊比利亚、安塔利亚发现的锡…
in Iberia, in Anatolia,
在英国、伊比利源里…
in Afghanistan. Okay?
in Afghanistan.Okay?
Copper is mainly found in Cyprus
?
and Crete and
和克里特岛以及在安塔利亚里…
also in Anatolia.
在…
Okay? Now, meaning
OK? 现在…
and what this means is in order to make bronze,
?
you basically have to trade with the entire world.
你们要把...??
Okay? So India,
...
this world,
这个世界，
the trading would go as far as from India to the Middle East.
从印度到中东的贸易将会延伸至此
From India to Britain.
From ... ... ... …
Even China over here was part of this world
翻译
but not to the degree as these other places.
...
Okay? In this world,
OK? 在此...??
there are different ways that you can profit or make money.
...
Okay? The first way is mining.
OK? 先后??
So basically extracting resources, tin and copper in order to make bronze.
...
Second way is industry manufacturing.
Right? So turning,
...
so making bronze from tin and copper
and then turning bronze into weapons,
和……把金属制成武器，
into pottery to be sold elsewhere.
把金属制成金属制成金属制成…
Okay? The third way you can make money is by what?
好的？第三种赚钱方式是什么？
Trading. Right? So
好吧！……………
in this world, if you look at this map, who is the most important person in the world?
在这片世界里，如果看这张地图，谁是世界最重要的人？
Basically profit the most from trading.
基本上是那种最能赚取利润的商人。
If you look at this map, who would make the most money from trading?
...
This area, right? Does that make sense?
Because it is the center of the world,
...
you have to pass through this world in order to access everywhere else.
??
Okay? And this place over here,
...
you look at the map, it becomes the center of the world
because this place.
因为这地方…
This place becomes the logistics hub of the world.
...
To get to anywhere, you have to pass through this place.
到达任何地方都要经过此处。
And so this place can basically collect tolls.
到达此处后再往后面
Right? This place is called what?
对了！这就是...??
Do you guys know? Yeah,
??
it's the toll gate of the world.
它是世界的关口。
Right? You have to pass through this place in order to access other places.
对了，先到此处才能到达其他地方。
Therefore, this place is very wealthy.
...
This place, can you guess what this place is called?
You guys, can you guys guess?
你们好！能给我来个...
Troy. Have you guys heard of the Trojan War?
Troy...??
Okay, we will do the Iliad next semester.
好的，下一学期我们会做《伊利亚特》
We will discuss the Iliad in the next class.
我们在下一节课里讨论《伊利亚点》
But I want you to understand this place is called Troy.
但我想让你们知道这地方叫做特洛伊。
And because this place is so important, for centuries,
因为它是个很重要的地方，长久以来一直是…
they've been fighting wars over this place.
…
Because it's really the center of the universe.
因为它是宇宙的中心。
Right? If you can control this place, you become very wealthy because everyone has passed through you.
对吧？如果能在此处掌握一手，便可把握手掌握。
You can collect tolls.
…
You can trade. Okay?
你可以做交易。好吗？
Does that make sense? And the last way you can make money off this world is what?
它们好像？…
What's the last way in which you can make a lot of money in this world?
…
You can do it through mining, industry, trading.
你可以通过矿业、工业、贸易来做事。
What else can you do to make money?
你还可以做什么来做事？
Piracy, right? Does that make sense?
…
Steal. Right?
???
Piracy. Right?
So, when we read the Iliad, what you will discover is the Greeks
...
who attacked Troy, they were basically pirates.
Troy made a lot of money off trading and
Troy...
pirates went to steal a lot of their resources
...
and, well, okay, does that make sense?
??
So, the main point is that
...
this world was interconnected.
It was a globalized world.
它是一个全球化的世界。
We call this globalization. But at the same time,
我们把它称为全球化。但与此同时，
it was very chaotic.
它很混乱。
It was very dynamic.
它很动态。
Okay? They traded with each other, but
好的？他们互相交易，但他们也相互交战。
they also fought wars against each other.
好的！】】
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这有道理吗？
And these places in the center of the universe might seem inglorious.
这些地方在中…
So, the Greeks, okay, became very wealthy because
So…...……………
they traded and they engaged in piracy.
...……………
The Hittites became very wealthy.
希特人变得非常富裕。
Egypt became very wealthy.
埃及人变得非常富裕。
Okay? Because they were the center of the universe.
好的？因为它们是宇宙的中心。
But a couple of decades later,
好的，几乎两年后，
this entire world collapsed.
整个世界坍塌了。
This world disappeared, meaning that
这个世界消失了，意味着……
Mycenaean Greece was destroyed.
米塞尼希腊的希腊已被毁灭。
It was completely burned down.
...
And they lost about a quarter of their population.
他们失去约四分之一的人口。
Okay? The Hittite Empire?
好的，哈希特帝国？
Destroyed. And even though Canaan disappeared,
已毁灭。 但也可说，古巴尼亚…
and even though Egypt was not destroyed,
...
it ceased to be a hegemon.
它停止了霸权。
It ceased to be a global power.
它是全球性力量的终结。
And a few decades later, they were conquered by outside powers.
几百年后，他们被外部势力征服。
Okay? After 1200 BCE,
...
Egypt ceased to be a power.
埃及停止成为强国。
So, this is what we call the Bronze Age Collapse.
这就是我们所说的青铜时代崩溃。
And for the decades,
并且在十几年的时间里，
scholars have been trying to figure out what happened.
学者们正在尝试去找出那时的事情
Why is it that in 1200 BCE,
...
this world was wealthy,
it was interconnected, and
它是相互联通的，且
then a few decades later, it all disappeared.
几百年后，才会出现…
It collapsed. And that's a great mystery that
…………………
no one has been able to solve.
155: no one…
Okay? So, let me tell you what we know.
...…
We know that
??…
what caused this collapse are what we call the Sea Peoples.
...
Sea Peoples. And we know because
Egypt has written
...
records of battling the Sea Peoples.
战斗海人记录。
So, basically, over the course of a few decades,
基本上，几经数十年，
people were coming in from the west and attacking Egypt.
从西方来袭的海人攻击埃及。
Okay? This was not one people.
...
This was a series of different people attacking Egypt from the sea.
And
Egypt had to spend decades in order to repulse the Sea Peoples.
埃及需要花费数十年时间来击退海人。
What we know is the Sea Peoples, whoever they were,
我们知道的海人是...
they did destroy Egypt, but
他们做了...…
they did destroy the Hittites, and they did destroy the Mycenaean Greeks.
...
Okay? So, and
what we know is the Sea Peoples,
...
they were basically, they were basically, they were basically a combination of pirates
他们基本上是，基本上是，基本上是，基本上是，基本上是，基本上是，基本上是，基本上…
and also refugees.
他们的确是…
These people attacked Egypt because
这些人攻击埃及，因为
Egypt was the breadbasket of the world.
埃及是世界的粮仓。
That's where all the food was. So, they were attacking Egypt for the food.
那是所有食物所在之处。所以他们攻击埃及是为了抢夺粮食。
Okay? These are people who are hungry.
好的？这就是吃了个吃没吃的？
They joined with pirates at ships, and they were trying to take over Egypt together.
他们与船上的海盗合伙，合伙去抢夺埃及。
They destroyed Mycenaean Greeks.
他们已破坏了希腓尼亚的古希腓尼亚人。
They destroyed the Hittites, but they failed to destroy Greece.
他们已破坏了古希腓里亚的古希腓里亚人
They were stopped, they were stopped in Egypt.
他们在埃及停住了。
Okay? So, another question then is,
好的，接着又是个问题：
what's driving this population movement from west to east?
从西向往来回的那点儿
Okay? That's a great mystery.
好的？那是个大谜题。
And over the past few decades,
在过去的几十年里，
different solutions, different ideas have been proposed.
不同的方案与思路已被提出。
Okay? Before, we thought that
好的？之前我们以为那是一次入侵。
it must have been an invasion.
它们的前面，先前方的先前方…
So, the idea is, that what's happening is, you have to destroy Egypt.
Okay, and you have
好的，且...
to destroy占卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬卬
???
natural disaster. So
]}We need to translate cues [192] and [193] into Simplified Chinese. The cuesare given as lines with some garbled text. Let's parse them. Cue [192] text:
the idea is maybe there was a volcanic explosion somewhere, okay?
在此处…………………………………………………………
And this caused the weather to change.
...
And now farmers could no longer feed themselves,
在此处……...
so they may start to move westwards and attack Egypt, okay?
...
That's the second theory. And there's more evidence for this,
but the theory
...
that we have today is a perfect storm, okay?
}]
Or a systems collapse.
...
And the idea here is that
it was not one thing in one year
that caused the system to collapse, it was a series of events over decades,
...
okay? And these three major events are
natural disasters, or so basically earthquakes.
自然灾害，或者说地震。
So we have archaeological evidence that
我们有考古证据表明
there is a series of earthquakes in this region at this time.
此时此地有一连串地震，
Which destabilized the region, okay?
此时此地的地震序列导致了地震序列的地震序列…
So earthquakes happened. We also have evidence of climate change,
自此地震发生后，...
okay? So the weather became cooler over the course of this period,
自此…
which meant that it was harder to grow crops, okay?
212: 1/2
And we also have evidence of eternal revolt,
...
okay? Meaning that people rebelled against the elite,
好的？这意味着人们起义反对精英，
overthrew kings,
?
and there was a lot of war and violence.
...
So the theory that
we have today is what caused the Bronze Age collapse was a perfect storm,
我们今天的内容是………………………………………………………??…………………………??……??………??……1?……………………………………?……..???…………古……??????……???……??? 1???? 1…………………地????……??…………………………………………………………………………………
basically a multiple factor which led to systems collapse.
翻译结果
Okay, does that make sense guys?
OK? 先后回到?
Any questions so far?
翻译结果
Any questions so far? Are we clear?
任何问题吗？
All right, so one thing that
...
you have made notice in this class is that,
?? ? ?? ?? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ???? ?? ?? ?? ?? ……… ? ? …???…??…………………………………………………………………………………
I have a very different understanding of history than other people,
okay? So I happen to disagree
...
with this theory of the first storm, even though it is the scholarly consensus,
翻译结果
all right? So I want to explain to you today my theory of what happened.
All right, so
...
the first thing you need to understand is this system collapsed even
though it was traumatic for Europe.
翻译结果
It is not unique in human history.
它在人的历史中并非唯一。
So what happened? This sort of stuff has happened before, okay?
So if we go over here to North America,
如果你们从这里往北去，去到达尔·拉尔…
to the Mayas, okay?
...
So the Maya civilization existed in Central America, okay?
玛雅文明在中美洲存在，好的？
Or Guatemala, basically.
玛雅文明在中美洲…
And so we find a similar pattern where in about 200 AD, okay?
在大约200年左右，出现了类似的模式，好的？
In the year 200, their civilization started to explode, okay?
在200年，文明开始爆发，好的？
It started to increase. It reached its peak at about
它开始增长。它在约900年达到顶峰，好的？
900 AD, okay?
In the year 900, its civilization was over the place in Central America.
在200年，文明在中美洲展开。
But then after 900,
在200年………………??
it went all the way down, okay?
它一路下降，好吗？
So about 30 years' time, by 1200,
大约1200年左右，约30年后，
they're basically, their entire civilization almost collapsed.
在此时，文明已几乎全落
So it's a very similar pattern
它是一个非常相似的模式
to what's happening in the Bronze Age.
它的...??
So the question then is, why does this happen?
...
Why does this happen? All right?
And so to understand this,
我想给你们一个新…
I am going to present you with a new theory
I am going to presentyou with a new theory
that we will use a lot in this class.
那我们会在这门课里用到很多
So I want you to understand this theory, okay?
那句...??
But it comes from a historian by the name of Peter Turchin.
但它来自一位名叫彼得·图尔奇恩的历史学家。
Peter Turchin, who's a historian.
彼得·图尔奇恩是历史学家。
He's American, but he came over from Russia.
他是美国人，但从俄里来回到…
He's basically Russian -American. And
他是…
he has a theory called elite overproduction.
他有一个叫做精英过剩的理论。
And elite overproduction,
翻译句段
the theory is very interesting because
...
it's arguing against the way
we traditionally understand why societies collapse, okay?
我们传统上理解社会为何崩溃，好的？
So the way we usually understand why societies collapse is we get from Karl Marx.
我们在常见的方式里，回到卡尔·马尔斯的...
And basically, what Karl Marx says is eventually your society collapses
基本上，卡尔·马克思所说的是，最终你的社会会崩溃
because the people revolt, okay?
因为人们回到？
So basically, people rebellion.
基本上，前面说的那句…
So in other words, Karl Marx believes that
所以换句话说，卡尔·马尔斯认为
society collapses because it is a bottom -up process,
社会会在底层起步的过程而出现
okay?
好的？
It's a bottom -up process.
基本是从底层开始的过程。
If you treat workers badly, they will stop working.
如果把工人们的工作方式去掉？
If you force them to work, they will go on strike.
如果把工人们...??
If you force them to work again, they will fight against you.
如果再把他们放到工作里，...
They will rebel, okay? A worker revolution.
...
Okay, that's what Karl Marx argues.
And Peter Turchin says, okay, that's a really interesting theory,
帕特里克·图尔奇恩说：这是一种非常有趣的理论，
but if you look at the historical data, if you look at the evidence,
帕特里内尔·图尔奇恩...??
the problem is in the bottom, okay?
先前…??
If you look at why societies collapse, it's not because of the people rebelling.
如果你观察社会崩溃的原因，它是因为…
it's because there's infighting among the elite.
...
So there's civil war among the elite.
Does that make sense? That's his theory.
翻译1
If the problem with society isn't that
翻译2
there's too many poor people,
翻译...
the problem is there are too many rich people.
问题在于富人太多。
That's the real problem. And that's why societies collapse.
这是个好句子！
Alright, so let me explain to you this theory slowly, okay?
...
Elite overproduction.
首选翻译1
Alright. Alright.
...
Okay, it's fine. Alright, so
in this world of 1200 BCE,
在公元前1200年的世界里，
we have something called a permanent,
有一种被称为永久的
hereditary, elite, okay?
世代世传的精英，
Permanent, hereditary, elite.
永久、世代世传的精英。
Permanent just means they're always there, okay?
永久只是指它们一直存在，好的？
Hereditary means they pass on their status and their privilege and their wealth to the children.
世代世传意味着它们把状态、特权和财富传给子孙。
And this is new in human history
在此处是人类历史的新篇章
because before there was an elite,
因为先前有个精英阶层
but they were not permanent, meaning they could be changed over time.
但又是个别样的古老阶层！
And they didn't pass their privileges on to their children.
他们把特权传给子孙。
Everyone had to earn their privilege and power.
每个人都要去赚取特权与权力。
Okay? So the elite was constantly shifting in society.
好的，先前的精英阶层是个别样的古老…
But now in about the year 1200 BCE,
但在公元前1200年左右，你有了一个世袭的精英阶层。
you had a permanent hereditary elite.
当时有了这一点，便有了三种优势。
When you have that, you have three advantages.
When you have that, youhave three advantages.
Okay? What the elite gives society are three major advantages.
好的？精英给社会带来的三大优势。
The first major advantage is the idea of organization.
第一个主要优势是组织的概念。
Okay? So the idea of organization is that you have to be a leader.
好的，组织概念就是要先行领导。
Right? Basically think of the elite as your brain, as society's brain.
右？把精英想成社会的脑袋吧。
They can help ornate resources, okay?
他们能帮忙装点资源，好的？
And that's good for war.
而且能为战事发光。
If you're fighting an enemy, you need an elite to lead you into battle, okay?
如果你在战斗敌人，得先有精英来领你去战斗。
It's also good for public works.
它也好于作工。
Okay? So think of the pyramids in Egypt and the Great War of China, right?
好吧，先把…
You need an elite to, um,
你需要一个精英来，呃，
organize your resources in order to create public works that benefit all society.
组织资源以便于建造公共工程，便于…
So the main thing here would be irrigation, right?
…
Yes? So you need an elite in order to have irrigation. So
是的？所以你需要一个精英来实现灌溶。于是……
that's the first major benefit of having a permanent hereditary elite.
那是个先前的先后之先后。
Second major advantage is because you have better organization, you have more wealth.
第二个大类的后期…
Okay? So
好的？所以
it becomes wealthier, if you have a permanent elite.
它会变得更富裕，如果有永久的精英。
People work harder.
人们会更努力工作。
Okay? And even though there's more inequality,
好的？ 甚至在有更多不平等时，
inequality also forces people to work harder.
不等于此时，给人们更好工作。”】}We need to translate cues 325-327. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate each cue. Ensure Chinese natural. Use line breaks if needed. Let's produce translations. Cue 325:
Does that make sense? Okay?
? Actually cue 325:
And because you have these two things, organization and wealth,
因为你拥有这两件事——组织和财富，你也拥有规模。
you also have scale.
规模基本上就是指你的人口可以再扩张。
And what scale basically means is your population now can move up.
And what scale basically means isyour population now can move up.
Before, in the egalitarian society,
译文1
when you didn't have a permanent elite, at most society could reach about 10,000 people.
译文2
But now when you have a permanent elite,
译文3
you can reach about a million people.
...
Okay? So now you can scale up.
OK? 现在可以扩展到...
So these are three major advantages
...
to having an elite.
拥有一个精英阶层。
Okay? But there's a problem with having an elite.
好的？但有一个问题是...
And the problem is they engage in
和...
something called rent -seeking behavior.
...
All right? I want you guys to remember this term, rent -seeking behavior,
好的？我想让你们记住这个词，租金寻求行为，
which is very important for our class.
好的，...
So what does this mean?
...
It means basically,
so think of a landlord, right?
A landlord doesn't really do anything, but a landlord has land
that it can rent to you, the farmer,
that it can rentto you, the farmer,
in exchange,
翻译结果：
you give me a share of your crops.
...
Right? So I don't do anything, but because I have land, I can rent it out to you.
Right? It turns out the elite
右？它会出现的精英
mainly make their money through rent -seeking behavior.
翻译...
So let me give you another example of rent -seeking behavior.
让我再给你们一个租金行为的例子。
All of you want to go to university, right?
全部 好 好 ?? ????
Why do you want to go to university?
为什么要去大学？
What's your purpose? Okay.
我想去上学的原因是？
What's your purpose in going to university?
先前的...???
Be honest. It's to get the degree,
?
right? Okay?
右？好？
The degree. Okay?
学位的...
And the degree is your ticket
和学位就是你的入场券
to success in society, okay?
学位就是要去的好时机
You believe that you go to university,
你认为你去大学是...??
you are getting a ticket, the degree,
?
in order to access social mobility,
okay? To access wealth in society.
好的？在此处可获得社会财富。
In other words, the universities are charging you rent, okay?
在此处………………………………
So the degree is basically rent. Does that make sense?
此处…………??
Okay? Now, some of you may say, wait,
好的？现在，你们中有些人可能会说，等一下，
that's wrong because I'm going to university to learn, right?
]}We need to translate? We need? ...?………..……..…………?………..……..……………………………..……..………
It's about learning. Well,
]..??..??…………..……..…..
guess what? When you actually go to university, you're going to discover
...
they don't actually teach you that much, okay?
They don't have to teach you that much and the reason why is you're stuck paying the rent.
...
You need the degree, right?
你需要拿到学位，对吗？
So you don't have to actually teach anything.
所以你就能把它写成…
You have to come to class anyway.
翻译：
Does that make sense? The same thing for the school
...
where in order to get to university, you have to go through this high school.
So you're here paying tuition and you're paying rent.
...
Does that make sense? You're not here in the school to learn,
you're here in school to get the degree
...
so you can access university and get that degree,
翻译：
okay? And all this process, all you're doing is paying rent.
...
So if you are, if you have a school,
385: 你可以在此处...
you can charge for rent.
385?
Just as if you're a landlord,
正如你是房东，可租金租金…
you can charge for rent for renting your room or real estate property, okay?
正如…
Does that make sense? This is what we call rent -seeking behavior.
翻译：
Okay? Now, you're like, okay, well,
?
this kind of sucks, okay?
这类...??
And it does suck. But
??
what keeps the system together is the idea of a social contract.
393: 何为系统之合一，乃是个别…
Okay? Basically, the idea of social contract is, yes, we the elite,
?
we know we are charging you rent and
我们知道我们在给你们充当租金，...??
we know this sucks for you, the people,
?
but we have a contract.
So as the elite, I'm obligated to help society.
]}We need to output JSON with translations array of 3 items. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use simplified Chinese. Let's translate cues 397-399. Provide array in order. Let's produce translations. Ensure no extra keys. Output exactly {
Okay? So
? Wait format: {
the way they help society is by giving back to society, okay? So
他们的帮助方式是把回馈给社会，好的？ 于是…
what the elite do throughout society in the past is they organize public feasts.
他们在过去的社会中组织了公祭，好的？ 也就是…
Okay? And also public temples.
好的，公祭和公祭…
So in today's society, you know, like the parks,
好的？于是…
the schools, the temples, they're built by the government, right?
他们的帮助方式是把回馈给社会，好的？ 于是…
But back then, they didn't have a government, they had the elites who were responsible
他们在过去的社会中组织了公祭…
for building temples,
为建寺庙，
for building, for holding public feasts.
为建造，举行公祭。
Okay? So this is the idea of a social contract.
好的，...
Okay? And the reason why you need a social contract is
好的？而且要有社会契约的原因是
because if you don't have a social contract and you just charge rent,
因为…
people will leave.
...
Does that make sense? Okay?
好？这有道理吗？
So in this world, it's very chaotic, but there are different places,
在这个世界里，...
there are different social organizations you can go to.
在此处…
So if you are in Egypt and you don't really like Egypt, guess what?
如果你在埃及里，...
You can go to Mesopotamia.
...
Okay? So these cities were in competition with each other for people
because people provided labor and resources.
因为人们提供劳动力和资源。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
好的，? 先前?
So this is how it usually works.
...
But over time, this system will break down.
Okay? This system will break down.
好的？这个系统会崩溃。
And it's because of rent -seeking behavior.
好的，...
Okay? So the first issue is this.
好的？第一个问题是这个。
With rent -seeking behavior,
...??
you create something called debt.
你创造了一个叫做债务的东西。
Okay? So I'm a landlord
好的，我是个地主。
and you are paying me rent in order to use my land,
在此时，...??
right? And that land,
??????..??
and that rent is usually a portion of your crops.
和租金通常是作物的一部分。
Okay? So you, does that make sense?
好的，先前一段】
Maybe 10% of your crops.
也许10%作物
But let's just say, for example, it's a bad year.
但让我们举例，假设是个好年
It doesn't rain. Okay? And you don't have any crops to pay me rent.
在此时...??
So what do you do? You're supposed to pay me a rent,
]}We need to translate cues 434 and 435. Provide JSON with translationsarray of two strings. Use simplified Chinese. Let's translate: cue 434:
but you don't have the money, so what do you do?
??
No, that comes later. What do you do first?
Exactly. Thank you. Yes.
??
Okay. So the first thing that happens is boring.
好的。第一件事先是个空空的...??
Okay? You're basically going to debt.
??
Okay? So
you promise to pay me double in the next year.
??
And I'm like, okay, fine. Right?
我想说：好，没问题！
But you get unlucky and the next year,
我方块块…??
it's also a bad year. And so for five years in a row,
它也是个好年，...??
you, you are in debt.
...
The problem with debt is this.
It's something called compound interest.
...
Okay? Meaning like over time,
好的？意思是随着时间推移，
the debt becomes so large,
...
there's no way you can pay it off.
If you can't pay it off, what happens now?
...
..
翻译成中文
...... Okay,
?
good, yeah, so the idea is debt slavery, okay?
翻译成中文
So you can't pay me back,
??
you become, you become my slave, okay, you promise me that
you become...?
your children work for, work for me for free,
???
okay? And so,
OK? 于是…
debt slavery, becomes the natural product of rent -seeking behavior,
?
does that make sense? Over time, you're always going to have a percentage of your population
翻译成中文
who go into debt slavery,
]}
okay, And this creates a lot of instability in society
好的，随后这会产生多重的变动。
because obviously they either want to run away or they want to rebel.
好的，后续…
Okay? Does it make sense?
好的？这有道理吗？
The other problem is
另外一个问题是
Elite overproduction And
精英过度生产
the idea here is
这里的意思是
Everyone wants to be the renter, right?
每个人都想当租客，没错吗？
Everyone wants to be the landlord, right?
每个人都想当租金？
But there's only so much land
但有只有几块土地
So now people are competing for
...
The power to charge rent.
Does it make sense? Okay,
...
so over time in any society
As a population increases
...
No people who go into that slavery increase
在 48 里 里 里 ????????????????????????????????????????
and therefore people at the bottom are very angry
]}We need to translate cues 478-480. Provide JSON array translations. Each string may contain at most one newline. Use simplified Chinese. Let's translate each cue in order. Provide array of 3 translations. Let's craft Chinese lines. Use terms:
and At the same time
? Let's produce.478:
the elite, the number goes up, but
...
there's only A set amount of land
and therefore they have to fight over the land
...
Okay Does it make sense and
So eventually what happens is
...
The society goes into War okay
I see elite fight each over,
...
as elite fight each other For the占 the right to charge rent.
Doesn't make sense. And so
...
the main message of elite overproduction is
主信息是精英过剩，若不控制人数，社会会出现崩溃。
unless you can control the amount,
主句子句...
the number of the elite in your society, your society must collapse.
...
Doesn't make sense. It must collapse
because you have too many people fighting for too little power.
...
It must collapse. So
historically, what are things you can do to control the elite?
历史上...
What are things you can do to control the number of the elite?
...
Jimmy? Kill the elite?
Okay. So,
好的。
but then where does the property go?
好的，...
Okay, so
好的，接着说。
one possible thing you can do is the idea of land redistribution.
一条可选的方案是土地分配。
Okay? So historically,
...
this is one mechanism you can use
to control the growth of the elite.
控制精英的增长。
And this is how kings can do it.
王之所作之法。
So the king came into power. Okay? So most societies have an elite.
507 译文：王 好 好 好！
And then one person from the elite said,
]}We need to translate cues 507 and 508. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate: cue 507:
listen, this society's not working.
...
Let me redistribute the land and
让我重新分配土地
cancel debt in order for our society to keep on going.
...
Okay? And this person became the king.
So that's one possible solution.
We have...??
Okay? What's another possible solution?
...
The question of the mandatory.
译文
Jimmy?.
...
....
Okay. So you can also have a civil war.
好的。你也可以有内战。
Okay?. Civil war.
好的？内战】
. Okay.
. 好的。
The elite can fight amongst themselves.
精英们可以相互打斗。
And whoever wins, gets everything.
谁赢了，便得到一切。
Okay? So it's a second possible solution.
好的？
What's another possible solution?.
...
What's another possible solution?
Empire building, right?
...
Does that make sense? Empire building.
在此处...
In other words, let's not fight amongst ourselves,
...
let's go and conquer new territory.
It doesn't make sense. So because
它不太好...
you have a permanent territory elite,
你有一个永久领土精英，
over time they're going to reach a mass, too many people.
在时间里他们会到达一个大集体，太多人。
We have too many elite, you have to resolve this issue through three ways.
我们有太多精英，需用三种方式解决此问题。
The first thing you can do is kill the elite and redistribute the land.
第一步可先把精英杀掉再分配土地。
That's what a king does. The second thing you can do is have a civil war.
...
The third thing you can do is create an empire.
But these three solutions by themselves are also unfair.
但这三种方案本身也不公平。而且稳定，行吗？因为土地再分配基本是革命。
And stable, okay? Because land redistribution is basically a revolution.
So war is war.
所以战争就是战争。
Empire building is also war.
帝国建设也是战争。
Does that make sense? So
那算是吗？那么就好啦！
no matter how you do these things, you're always going to create instability.
不管怎样做，都是要去做的。”
And eventually your empire,
...
your society will collapse.
Does that make sense? So.
...
Let me give you another example of how this works.
让我再给你举个例子说明这件事。
To clarify for you, okay? So
为了给你更好理解，先给你说个好例子。
there's a book called Capital in the 21st Century by Thomas Piketty.
...
Thomas Piketty is a French economist.
And this is a very famous book that's been recently published.
...
And in the book,
he looked at the past 100 years of economic growth.
他看过了百年经济增长的历程。
And what he discovered over
和...
time is the
...
financial economy grows faster than the real economy.
财务经济增长速度快于实体经济。
Capital grows faster than manufacturing.
资本增长速度快于制造业。
Okay? So if you look at capital,
...
it grows at 5%.
Real economy grows at 2%.
...
Alright? Right? So if things stay stable over time,
this will happen to all societies.
这将发生在所有社会中。
Capital will grow faster than the real economy.
资本将比实体经济增长得更快。
What this means is, let's just say you have a million dollars, okay?
这意味着，先说你有一百万元，好的？
I have a million dollars. I have different options to invest my money.
我有一百万元，能有多种选择去投资。
I can start a factory or I
我可以开设工厂，或者我
can put all my money into real estate or the stock market.
我可以把所有的资金投入到房产或股票市场。
Where should I put my money? I can open a factory, right?
...
Or I can put it in the stock market.
Where should I put my money?
...
Yes and why?
是的，为什么？
Exactly. You understand? If you have money today,
确切地说，能否给我一条…
you do not put your money into the factories.
...
You do not open a new business.
你们没开新业务。
You put it in the stock market because you make more money that way.
我把它放在股票市场里…
What's the problem with that? Okay? I have
{
more resources,
more resources
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more…
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
?
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
?
more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources, more resources,
??
more resources, more resources,
???
more resources,
]}????????????????????????????..??..??..
more the rent seeking behavior we have too many people doing
?..??..???…..?…..?…..
that you have a society where nobody works
{
doesn't make sense nobody does any work because
?
all the well is being put into rent sinking
?..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..
behavior it's being put into speculation
??
so no one's doing any more work no one's creating more wealth
???
and this eventually leads to social collapse at some
point okay does it make sense all right
点数好，没错？
so Peter torchins theory of elite overproduction is
??
because
the number of rich people can only go up
??
over time your society must
clap at some point unless you choose to have a revolution
??
or you have a civil war or you go invade other countries okay those are your three options
...
but you need but if you did that that
??
creates more instability so
over time no matter how how you
...
structure your society it will collapse does
??
that make sense okay so
that's what happened during the branch it's collapsed
...
where these societies must have in Greece high tides
??
each of canane they were fundamentally unstable
...
because of red seeking behavior okay saving with the Mayans
where okay they were going very fast but
??
eventually they clapped all studies will do this
at some point no society is stable
...
okay the reason why is you have an elite in charge
who
...
helped society grow over time they will just engage in red seeking behavior
which will eventually lead to collapse of society okay
??
so that's why I'm saying that the only way to get rid of the red seeking behavior is to have a civil war right and
so that's why I'm saying that the only way to get rid ofthe red seeking behavior is to have a civil war right and
this is a pattern that we'll see over and
this is a pattern…
over again in human history and
we'll discuss this idea throughout this
...
semester all right doesn't
???
make sense any
在此处...??
questions all right
?
so let's look at a very specific example of
让我们来看看一个非常具体的例子：在希腊里…
red seeking behavior my city in Greece I'm going to talk about the red seeking behavior in Greece all right my city in Greece
?
so my city in Greece and
在此处...??
you may remember this from last class it was a long time ago
在此类…??
but last class we talked about the
...??...??...???
Yemnaya right the Yemnaya right they conquered Europe
...????...???
so the my city in Greece and
translations
the high tides are direct descendants of the Yemnaya
?
and as you remember this is a warrior culture okay so
...???????????????
these societies are warrior societies meaning
...??????...??????…
like the warriors are in charge and
...????...??????
they have a system called
...
a palace
economy a
翻译1
palace economy a palace economy is basically the palace is at the center of society
翻译2
and
...??...????...???
everyone brings their wealth to
...??????????
the palace to be redistributed to everyone else okay
...??...????...???
so the idea here is we're all farmers right and
...???????
maybe you could say that the you have 100 100
...??...??...??...???
bushels of wheat maybe 20
...??...??..???
bushels of corn okay everyone brings everything to the palace
...??...??...??..???
and then
...??..??..???
the king redistributes the everything to you okay
国王把一切重新分配给你，好吗？
but obviously he takes a cut understand
他还会把它们分给其他人。
so this is called red seeking behavior where
翻译：
I'm where you're basically paying taxes okay does it make sense
...??????..??..???
okay now this is fine
when things are good okay
when things aregood okay
but
?
if there be the weather becomes
如果有……………………………………………………
bad this system starts
]}We need to translate cue [653] and [654] into Simplified Chinese. The cues: [653] if there be the weather becomes [654]bad this? Wait the cues: [653] if there be the weather becomes [654] bad this system starts. Actually the original text:
to collapse why the
翻译到 ？
weather is bad things
start to become chaotic why
...
okay the reason why is the lead still okay the reason why is the
lead still okay the reason why is the lead still what their cut you understand it's not what their cut you understand it's not what their cut you understand it's not like oh this year the weather is bad
???
so like oh this year the weather is bad so like oh this year the weather is bad so let's just suffer together okay let's let's just suffer together okay let's make sacrifices together no it's like no make sacrifices
...
together no it's like no make sacrifices together no it's like no we don't care the weather is bad you we don't care the weather is bad you we don't care the weather is bad you start to pay our pay our cut okay you start to pay our pay our cut okay you start to pay your taxes
start to pay
...
your taxes
that during the Bronze Age, there was an internal revolt
...
in Mycenaean Greece.
翻译后...
And the reason why is we can dig up Mycenaean Greece,
translations
the palace, and what we see is the palace is burned down,
...
but the surrounding houses are fine.
Okay, does that make sense? We also have written records from Mycenaean Greece
...
that show how the palace economy worked, okay?
We can also dig up the graves of the kings and show
我们可以挖掘王宫的墓葬，展示…
that over time, they became wealthier and wealthier
我们可以挖掂…
because when they were buried,
因为他们被埋葬时，与之相伴的物品非常昂贵。
the things they were buried with were very expensive.
因为他们被埋葬时，与之相伴随之而来。”
Does that make sense?
...
Okay, so that's Mycenaean Greece.
Any questions so far? Okay, it's clear about this idea.
任何问题吗？好了，关于这个想法已经清晰了。
Okay? So,
]}We need to translate cues 677 and 678. They are: [677] Any questions so far? Okay, it's clear about this... [678] Okay? So, ... We need to produce JSON with translations array of two strings. Use Chinese. Use line breaks if needed. Let's produce:
what a lot of scholars believe is
...
that this is,
the Bronze Age Collapse was a unique event in European history.
…
And what I'm trying to show you is,
...
it was not a unique event, it was not a revolution,
it's just part of the natural cycle of history.
...
Because when you have the elite, who engage in rhetoric and behavior,
因为当你有了……
eventually this society will collapse.
...
Because you have too many elite who want their cut.
因为你有太多的精英想要分一份。
And when we look at other societies,
...
you will discover this pattern repeats itself.
你会发现这个模式会重复出现。
Right? So, this is Peter Turchin,
好吧，...??
his theory of elite over production.
他的精英过度生产理论。
Are we clear? Yes?
我们好吗？
Okay, alright,
好的，好的，
so, okay, let me clarify, about Mycenaean Greece, okay?
All right, the problem is, that
好的，已知问题在于此：
you have too many rich people, who
好的，已知 … … …
wanna charge rent, right, and that creates pressure on society,
wanna...??
and this instability, Stability means that your society is no longer resilient.
好的，且…………………………………………………
Okay, resilient And
OK
the idea of resilience is that it survives disasters
...
Right. So think of a tower
That's about to collapse. Okay,
That's about tocollapse. Okay,
it will not clap on its own Something must hit it for it to collapse.
它会在自己的...??
But this one thing could be anything Okay, it could be the people get angry
...
and they riot it could be the weather turns bad Okay, it could be a there's an earthquake.
和他们起了骚乱，天气变得好像是…
It could be there's an invasion. Does it does that make sense?
它们的…
So these different societies, okay, my city agrees high tides
...
The Canaanites they class for different reasons
But the fundamental reason is because
of societies were unstable The reason why they were unstable is you had too many elite people
...
Trying to charge rent on everyone else.
翻译：
Does that make sense? Okay,
...
anyway any more questions, but that's a good question.
Thank you To me
...
Oh Can you avoid the cycle in today's society?
Okay, that's a good question and the answer is no
...
Okay, it is impossible to build a society
That that
...
is stable over a long period of time in fact You can make the argument
that it is good for societies to rise and fall Okay,
...
it's the same thing as it's really some question as is it possible for us to live forever
翻译1
Is it possible for us to live forever then the question then
]}We need to translate cues 721 and 722 into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSONwith translations array of two strings. Use terms. Let's translate: cue 721:
is why would we want to live forever?
...
You understand innovation happens when we die
Okay, so So what's amazing about the Bronze Age collapse is
OK...??
because of Bronze Age collapsed?
?
Mycenaean Greece changed
...
into a new society that gave us Greek civilization
Which then gave us Western civilization?
...
Okay So in other words if my city agrees
OK
that collapse we will not have today
OK? ? ???? ……??? …??? ??………………………………………………………………………
Also because kind of collapse a
…………
new society came into being called the Israelites, okay, Israel and
...
Israel gave us what you guys know
the Bible right
...
and guess what guys the Greeks and
the Bible are the two foundations of Western civilization
?
so we would not have Western civilization if this
翻译
Society that collapse and new studies could come into being
翻译后可用????????????????????????????????????????
All right, so you can make the argument that
...
innovation progress is driven by death
and collapse All right
???
You understand And
...
if we if we got die if we not if we do not die besides
that I collapse there'd be no progress
...
Okay Does it make sense?
OK
But that's a good question. Okay, but but and
...
people will happen debating this question for a long time But
I think the answer is it is impossible
...
to build a society that lives forever even
though people have tried and also we should even try okay, because
翻译成中文：
Collapse is good. Also think of a forest fire.
Collapse …? ? ?? … … ? ?
Have you guys studied forest fires in school in science class?
...
forest fires forest fires guys
Each time there's a forest fire
...
Okay, the force burns out.
OK
That's good Because
...
it allows the force to regenerate and become stronger
Right. What happens if you don't have a forest fire?
...
Did you guys know? Okay,
the resilience goes down
...
Okay, and also
OK
the ecosystem is less
...
Vibrant, they're less
Vibrant， 他们更少
They're less animals. The trees are less strong.
他们的动物更少。树木更轻。
Okay, do you understand? So that's why it's important to burn down the force now
好的，我明白了。于是这就是为什么要把它们放在一块大地块里。
and then you don't burn on the forest and there's
好的，能否给我方位？
then it's less resilient
then it’s...?
So there's a big forest fire
]}We need to translate cues 768 and 769. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate: 768
It was just bread and destroyed entire force.
它只是一份 ? …
Okay, does it make sense?
...
So it's good for societies to constantly change
over time Okay
...
Any more questions?
Okay, that's a great question, okay
...
All right So
好的，先说一下：
before we talk about egalitarian societies right how they were at most 10,000 people
先前往前说，先前…
and they did have an elite, okay?
...
They had an elite They had people in charge,
but this elite didn't own the property.
...
There's no private property. Okay, so it's egalitarian and
so These societies were pretty stable.
这些社会相当稳定。
Okay, and the reason why is
好的，原因是
Usually it was the woman in charge and
通常是由女人掌管的。
the woman could were good at controlling population Okay,
女儿可以控制人口的好处
because as a woman you have control over your body.
...
So you could choose not to have children or have less children
And it was very peaceful right people didn't really fight which there's nothing to fight over.
......
Everything was owned by everyone else
...
Okay, the problem with egalitarian societies are these three things Okay,
they're less organized meaning like they are less
它们更不组织化，像是它们更…
willing or less able to create public projects
它们更……
Okay, they have less wealth and therefore they have less scale.
好的，…
Okay, you can have at most 10,000 people
...
Which means what which means like
eventually Eventually, they will be conquered
...
Okay, does that make sense? Because
好的，...
if you are one of these societies, okay,
...
you're an empire you must constantly expand in order to
Please delete basically, okay,
请在此处删除…好吧！
either you expand or you fight a civil war and
我想……??
So that you take over egalitarian societies and you make them into your society.
…??
Okay, do you understand? so
好的，我懂了，先说一下：
For most of the human history were egalitarian,
可见...??
but that's because we didn't have that many people
?
Right But over time as population increases
译文1
Then you are less egalitarian you become more unequal
译文2
you stay egalitarian you will eventually be conquered by a
译文3
Not not an egalitarian society, does that make sense?
不是一个平等的...??
All right All right,
好吧...??
but that's a great question You're exactly right.
??
Okay for most of human history were egalitarian, but
好的，几乎所有人类的历史都很平等，...
once we start develop elite societies, okay
好的，...??
Kingdoms then it could easily conquer egalitarian societies
...
All right any more questions,
好的，...??
but but that's a fantastic question.
译文
Okay any more questions
??
And when we do so we are skipping ahead but when we do Samaria
...
Samaria Which is basically
Many different city -states in Iraq
...
Mesopotamia what we will discover is
Mesopotamia whatwe will discover is
that there are different social structures, okay
...
There are different social structures including societies that were egalitarian
But when you're in competition with each other societies that
但当你们在竞争中...
are more organized more wealthy now bigger populations will always win out over
是的，...
other societies Okay,
其他社会，好的，
you have these three things you need a permanent
你有这三件事，才需要永久
territory elite because then
领土精英因为随后
they are more incentivized in order to
???
Work harder, okay, does it make sense and then
工作更努力，好的，先...
the question then is okay?
...
Why is that true? And it's true because
为什么这件事有点儿…????
For societies become wealthier.
?????
You don't need everyone to work hard You just need a certain
你不需要人人都工作努力，你只需某些人工作努力。
number of people to work hard for You just need a small group of people to work hard.
你只需一个小组人工作劳作
It doesn't make sense. So think all like China, right?
它不太好...???
How China became wealthier?
]}
These past 30 40 years and
翻译1
the reason why is you had a small number of entrepreneurs who
翻译2
worked really really hard Okay, not everyone worked hard
翻译这句...
Okay, but because you have these people who did work really hard trying to become wealthier
好的，因...
Does that make sense? Okay any more questions?
...
Okay, so great.
Okay. So Again,
好的。
what makes this class different from other classes is we are looking at the entire scope of human history
再一次，
All right, and it's what's very important for you to not understand not remember the facts.
我们正在查看人类历史的全部范围。
Okay, I don't need you remember the facts Okay,
好的，我不需要你记住事实。
I don't need you remember my son he agrees or the sea people,
好的，...
but I do need you to remember the concepts and the ideas
好的...
Okay, how the world history is constantly in competition with each other
好的，世界历史不断相互竞争。
and Why is it that some ideas win out over other ideas?
好的，某些想法会在竞争中胜出。
Okay, so that's saying this is the best idea.
好的，先前的句子…
Okay. I'm not saying a permanent
好的。我不是说领土精英是个好主意。
Territory elite is a really good idea.
]}We need to translate cues 853-855. Provide array translations. Each string may contain at most one newline. Let's translate:
I don't think it's a good idea Okay, but
]} seems extraneous. We need to produce translations array with 3 items. Let's translateeach cue in order. Use natural Chinese. Use preferred terms? Not needed. Let's produce:
I'm showing you what wins out and how it impacts human history
and the development of civilization
Does that make sense? Okay
...
Okay, any more questions? Okay Okay, well that's it